"How to Boost Your Endothelial Progenitor Cells (EPCs)
for Heart Health"
How can we remain
young at heart?
The capacity of our blood
vessels to repair themselves
is dependent on
endothelial progenitor cells
that emerge from stem cells
in our bone marrow
to patch up any holes
in our endothelium,
the innermost lining
of our blood vessels
that keeps our blood
flowing smoothly.
Lower levels of circulating
endothelial progenitor cells
in the blood correlates
with arterial diseases
like erectile dysfunction.
Higher numbers,
on the other hand,
are correlated with
a significantly reduced risk
of death
from cardiovascular causes.
Before we explore
how to boost our levels,
let us first establish
cause-and-effect.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
was performed in men and women
with peripheral
vascular disease,
a circulation disorder
characterized by the narrowing
of blood vessels outside
of the heart or brain.
The arteries supplying
blood to their legs
were so ravaged by disease
that they could only
walk about a minute
before the muscles in their legs
cried out in pain
from lack of oxygen.
For each study participant,
one leg was randomly selected
to be injected with cells
from their own bone marrow
and the other was injected
with their own peripheral blood
as a control.
Not only was pain-free walking
time significantly extended
in the marrow-injected leg,
they were less likely
to subsequently lose it.
Severe limb ischemia,
lack of oxygen,
from peripheral
vascular disease
carries a 10 to 40 percent
amputation rate
within six months.
In the control group,
14 percent were forced
to undergo a major amputation
compared to zero
in the bone marrow group.
Given these remarkable benefits,
the link between higher numbers
of endothelial progenitor cells
and lower risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease
may indeed be causal.
Short of sticking a large bore
needle into your hip,
how else can we
cultivate and release
more endothelial progenitor
cells into our system?
Smoking cessation is one of the
most important and effective
lifestyle changes to increase
the number and function
of active endothelial
progenitor cells.
Cutting down isn't enough.
There are 20 cigarettes
in a pack.
If you only smoke
about one a day,
wouldn't you think you'd only
have one-twentieth the risk
of cardiovascular disease,
compared to smoking
the whole pack?
Based on a meta-analysis
of more than a hundred studies,
smoking only about
one cigarette a day
caused around 10 times the risk
of cardiovascular disease
you'd expect by that logic,
compared to smoking
a pack a day.
There is no
safe level of smoking
when it comes to heart attack
and stroke risk.
Even exposure to second-hand
smoke can deteriorate
our circulating endothelial
progenitor cell count,
so even just being
around smokers is risky.
Randomized controlled trials
show exercise training
can actually boost endothelial
progenitor cell circulation.
In a study of middle-aged
and older sedentary men,
for example, three months
of moderate aerobic exercise--
mostly walking,
with some participants
starting to jog a bit
as their fitness improved--
led to a doubling of
endothelial progenitor cells
in their bloodstream.
Regular aerobic exercise
could be considered
a "first line" strategy
for helping to prevent and treat
arterial aging.
What about diet?
A randomized controlled trial
showed that reducing
saturated fat,
mostly in the form of butter,
significantly elevated
endothelial progenitor
cell numbers,
consistent with a study
on baboons showing that
even a few weeks
of a high-cholesterol,
high-fat diet
could cause dramatic
premature epithelial
cell senescence.
Individual foods that
have been shown to increase
circulating endothelial
progenitor cells
include berries,
onions, and green tea,
and a diet centered completely
around whole plant foods
not only showed a boost
in endothelial progenitors,
but an improvement
in endothelial function,
along with a drop
in LDL cholesterol.